welcome to untangling the world knot of
consciousness
wrestling with the hard problems of mind
and meaning in the modern scientific age
my name is john verviki i'm a cognitive
psychologist and cognitive scientist at
the university of toronto in canada
throughout the entire series i will be
joined in dialogue by my good friend and
colleague
greg enriquez from james madison
university in the united states
throughout we are going to wrestle with
the hard problems of how we can give an
account
of a phenomenal like consciousness
within
the scientific worldview how we can
wrestle with that problem in conjunction
with the problem that greg calls the
problem of psychology
that is pervasive throughout psychology
which is that psychology has no unified
descriptive metaphysics
by which it talks about mind and or
behavior
throughout this we will be talking about
some of the most important philosophical
cognitive scientific and neuroscientific
accounts of consciousness
so i hope you'll join us throughout i
want you to note that
it's not only what we're saying but the
dialogical manner of the presentation
that's part of what we're arguing for
here in this discussion that's right
i i'll share that greg enriquez here and
i
uh i had a moment of inspiration i wrote
john i was like john
you realize that we're dialoguing about
the ontology of mind in a socratic
fashion
to usher in a new way of doing academic
work and
uh i i think with that that intersection
that made me really excited about this
project so thank you john for
this uh set of insights and at so many
different levels it's very very valuable
i think
well thank you greg i mean your
partnership is and your friendship
are much appreciated um and as well as
as your your vast uh reading and
relevant expertise
um none of these things that i'm
proposing and that's what they are
are are proposed as well of course this
is the case
this is the hardest the most difficult
thing we're trying to wrestle with
and so um doing it in a in a socratic
situation i think
is uh most uh the most
intellectually ethical way we can be
responsible
uh to the material and to the people who
might be listening
so last time we were taking a look i'm
presenting
so following on the idea of the
importance of problem formulation and
spending a lot of time
before trying to solve the problem and
just say what consciousness is or
there's a lot of that already i'm
proposing and greg is helping me
that we go through and really try to
formulate the
modern problem of consciousness as
clearly as possible
um and towards that end
what i'm doing greg are you still there
yeah yeah no i'm just i'm
enraptured set it up
so towards the end um what i proposed we
do is take a look
at um the arguments that are generally
considered to be
uh the classical presentation of the
problem
what i've been arguing is that uh and
these arguments
emerge within the context of the
scientific revolution
and they emerge around the pivotal
figure of descartes
and what i've been trying to argue is we
need to get that historical
formulation of the problem very clearly
in hand
before we then proceed uh to try and
unravel that
and then greg has been making uh
valuable insightful connections not only
is he giving me feedback on the
proposals
he's in addition making valuable
insightful connections to
the problem that he sees central he sees
it of course as related to this problem
the untying the world not
but the problem that is typified in his
uh tree of knowledge
and um next time uh or possibly the time
after that
uh greg is going to take the burden of
leading us through
presentation as he wrestles with and
hopefully i can be as helpful to him as
he has been to me wrestles with how this
problematic given to us by descartes and
the scientific revolution
has translated into what he calls the
problem of psychology
so that's sort of that's sort of where
we're going so today i want to try
with greg's help i want to try and
finish out the argument so last time we
took a look at an argument
by descartes that basically and now i'm
not going to try and make the argument
you know i'm not going to i please don't
accumulating i
i really uh last time tried to present
descartes argument in detail and
carefully
so this is now just a summary right
baker descartes is basically saying
well if you take a look at mind and
matter um there's
you know there are two kinds of stuff um
and they don't
seem to share any properties uh oh sorry
let's do it the other way around when we
take a look at the properties of mind
and matter
they don't seem to share any kinds of
properties what the properties that seem
to be central to mine
are not possessed in matter and vice
versa and so that leads into the
conclusion that there are radically two
kinds of stuff
and then i pointed out that that
argument is techno
technically not valid um and then i
pointed out an attempt to try
and keep it valid by moving from
properties of mind and matter to
essential properties of mind and matter
also doesn't turn out to be um
technically valid
and then what that leaves us with is
right
um the question of why is the argument
so influential if it's technically not
valid
and what i argued was is that descartes
was actually using
a form of argumentation that is central
to all of science which is inference to
the best explanation
and then if you put descartes proposal
for dualism
into competition with the other
contenders at that time
his proposal does the best so the one
the most prominent contender is of
course
uh the aristotelian worldview but the
scientific revolution is leading that
worldview into collapse
and and whereas descartes view seems to
be
directly um in sync with the emerging
scientific revolution
because he what his view does is remove
a lot of the problematic aristotelian
properties
from the world and put them in the mind
therefore leaving the world free
uh to uh to a more mathematical
and mechanical explanation he then um
also what he does is he then comes to
see the mind
almost exclusively in terms of its
capacity
uh for manipulating mathematical
propositions
the mind becomes a purely uh
mathematical epistemic engine and that's
because the old job of the mind
and the aristotelian worldview of
actualizing life
into agency and coupling us to the world
in the right way
has been lost uh in the scientific
revolution
and then descartes view is also in
competition with the
the late renaissance right uh
neoplatonic magicians
um i'm not invoking anything
supernatural here but that's
perhaps the best way and they were very
interested in things that are now
central to the emerging analysis of mind
they were interested in
actionable distance real relations
self-organization
and then descartes and one wing of the
catholic church sort of ally together
because they want that uh approach
to mind and life and reality completely
discredited and marginalized
uh because it it presents a very
significant
threat to the christian worldview
and so what remains therefore is a new
notion
of matter and a new notion of causation
matter is no longer pure potentiality
like it was for aristotle
matter is in actuality but it's only
act it's single act is the act of
raw resistance it is inert it is
inertial
it has no inner structure no inner
dynamic quality
it is in no way teleological uh and all
of the causation
has now collapsed into uh mechanical
causation
where these inert things smash into each
other and bump into each other
given that scientific world view
cartesian dualism
can out compete both uh
thus the declining uh aristotelian
worldview
it can help to marginalize the
neoplatonic magical view
and therefore best align
align itself with the emerging
scientific revolution really and what i
was therefore trying to show was
the scientific worldview and the
problematization of consciousness
go hand in hand not because that not not
because of an
initially antagonistic relationship
people often now
oh but consciousness and it's being
science
it was actually caught it was it was the
scientific revolution
that originally gave us this dualistic
picture of mine
the dualistic picture of mine is not
some new
radical way to respond to the way
science has dropped
you know emptied the world of all
meaning and mind
it was actually generated by the
scientific revolution by one of its
premier representatives which is daycare
so that's the first argument anything
you want to comment on that greg
yeah so so i i think that the reason we
want to do problem formulation here
folks
from my vantage point and i think from
john's also is
not only do we want to get a frame but
we also want to understand that we're
inheriting the grammar
i mean at least our culture is
inheriting the grammar of this history
of
what i would call this history of
justification uh this history of
narrative sense making
uh that we are a part of and the way in
which our grammar functions so that's
why it's so crucial
both for problem formation and to
understand kind of where we are and how
people tend to use language around these
terms so that's
that's one point as to why i want to
echo why this is so super crucial
the other thing i will say is that i i
want to
i'm going to be trailing this uh through
the more the matter in motion mentality
okay um which is galileo uh
and certainly in conjunction with
descartes but galileo into newton
and one thing i'll simply say is galileo
i think i might have mentioned this
before but i'll simply reiterate
galileo hates aristotle's metaphysics
because it's getting abused
in a particular way so he cuts off form
a
final causation um and formal causation
and leaves behind uh substance and
efficient or kinetic causation
so when john's doing this okay this
is in part also what galileo's doing
when he's watching matter in motion
all right and then you have descartes
and galileo both really
birthing in their own way the modern
scientific
um system and then you'll get to uh
newton who will essentially formalize
in in a macro way galileo's system
uh in a particular way and that's going
to take off it's the intersection of a
lot of these different things
uh down the line but so so that's what's
happening as
the sense making system and the other
thing i simply will say
from a psychological cognitive
dissonance every way how do we justify
ourselves the
it makes perfect sense to me
historically that rene descartes and the
catholic church will sort of come to a
compromise here
in this dualistic world view given the
powers that be and where they are
in the institutions and the sense making
systems that are operative
at this time thank you greg i do
i do agree with that i think that's
excellent so
why is what what's so okay so what's
wrong with descartes winning
um you know what what's wrong with all
and picking up on the connection between
galileo and descartes galileo divides
you know all of the properties all of
the qualities into two kinds
the mathematical ones uh which are
primary are taken to be objectively real
and then all the non-mathematical ones
are taken to exist only in the mind
those are the secondary qualities and
they are now the philosophers now refer
to that with the abbreviated term qualia
and and they only exist in consciousness
because they don't exist in the world
um and so why is all why is the
cartesian dualism problematic
and especially why like what's wrong
with consciousness being an immaterial
substance etc and all that sort of thing
the problem with that is while descartes
sort of wins all
the argumentative battles he and i think
this is something that uh
greg does excellent work on he loses we
all know he's losing
the experiential existential battle uh
because
i mean it is readily apparent to me that
there is
a profound intimacy and interpenetration
in my experience of mind and matter
if descartes was right mind can in no
way move
matter it has no physical energy it has
no inertial properties it has no
material resistance
there's no way mine can bang into any
material part of my brain so how is it
that my desire
to pick up my watch actually ends up in
the physical movement
of my watch like and then the reverse
how is it the material events i'll lead
to a
particularly uh
mental event within consciousness pain
this is the problem that descartes has
and this is not something oh no
everybody around descartes including
descartes realizes that this
is a profound problem and it's precisely
a profound problem because people
are convinced by descartes arguments and
we've just reviewed the first one
and yet they can't deny
the overwhelming like
evidence for mind-body interaction and
and again mind to mind interaction
because the only way i can pick up on
greg
right is there's photons coming out of
my tv screen it's a material event
and somehow that has a causal chain and
that if that causal chain
is all physical and it never can reach
the purely
immaterial mind that he possesses
then i can't actually ever know his mind
and and this has of course horrible
consequences
because if you think and we'll come back
to this later you think that animals
don't possess consciousness
um then of course there's nothing wrong
with you know
doing live uh dissections of them
because it's no different
than a bell ringing and things like that
[Music]
so and then you know uh there's all
kinds of
untoward consequences and and and
as i said uh greg is going to show how
those ramify
uh through uh the history of psychology
in ways that
have become as he's already indicated
woven into the very grammar by which we
talk about ourselves
and by which we pursue therapeutic
relief of our distress
this is how profound this problem is
this is how very you can't say oh well
this is
who cares about the philosophy i get it
in one sense but in another sense
and i think greg is deeply right about
this this gets into the guts of your
life
and your attempts to understand yourself
and alleviate any distress you might be
undergoing etc
excellent all right so that's the first
argument descartes has three
and they're all influential and they're
all part of the problem formulation
and any attempt to address the world not
of consciousness
has to address all three of these
arguments to be satisfactory
okay so what's the second argument the
second argument is
an argument around comparative realness
and descartes follows
a long-standing tradition and that and
it's even sort of presupposed
and nicholas maxwell has talked about
this within science of
and it goes back to promenities that
realness is sort of measured
uh by intelligibility how much sense we
can make of something how
uh and and this is why we think of
things like um
equals mc squared as profoundly real
because we can explain so much it
renders so much of the rest of the world
intelligible it must be deeply real and
so there's a deep connection between
realness and intelligibility so then
descartes basically makes an
argument which goes along the following
lines
the intelligibility of the body is
asymmetrically dependent on the
intelligibility of the mind
which means the mind is
by this argument inherently more real
than the body
and differences in realness are
we are differences in kind
so so the difference betw right is our
differences in kind
so let's give a concrete example uh of
one board from descartes and you can
think of the
the movie the matrix about this sort of
thing uh daycard says
well i can be dreaming that i have a
body
and i don't and in that dream that body
is not and here's the right
word it's not real that
that right that i can only actually make
sense of that body
by having a more direct
intelligibility a direct awareness of my
own mind
so this is where the kagito ergo sum of
descartes comes in
so essentially this is the very famous i
think therefore i am
which every freshman will tell you is
not an argument like that that's not an
argument that's not a
the conclusion doesn't follow for the
premise like what what the hell right uh
what descartes means is and we've talked
about this remember what we had with
aristotle was a contact epistemology a
conformity
uh epistemology uh and that
what descartes says is the only thing
the mind is now in conformity with the
only thing that participates in
is itself and and that is a feature of
consciousness
you know your consciousness by being
conscious and so
the mind has a direct awareness of
itself it is directly intelligible to
itself
it cannot doubt its own realness
for you to say i think my consciousness
is an illusion is like what
like right what does that that means no
sense so for descartes
well it is reasonable to entertain
the possibility that your body is an
illusion
it is not equally reasonable to
entertain the idea
that your mind is an illusion so it's
very possible that your body is only an
illusion
and therefore it is less real
than your mind and secondly how do i
know about my body and this is something
i want to call into question later but
this is descartes argument
well i start from the mind's direct
awareness of itself and then
the events in my mind and then i infer
that i have a body i infer that i have a
body and that inference of course
is a kind of abductive inductive
inference
and that means it's potentially fallible
the dream example shows you that
and so descartes says
the realness of the mind is inferior to
and completely dependent on the realness
of the body
and therefore the mind and the body must
be two kind
different kinds of things in order to
in order to give a good explanation
for why we have this suck this this
huge difference in realness so first of
all how does that argument
uh how's that yeah i think that very
important when you make the freshman
comment so let's make a distinction here
and i think you do this actually in your
course which i found to be very very
dead-on and i hadn't actually formulated
this way so in terms of logic
you know aristotle aristotelian logic
deductive argument
i think therefore i am is not great okay
but at the psychological
phenomenological level of being
it's a very very powerful argument you
know it really
really is it and and it is the case
within the dream
the evil demon dream argument um or even
a you know that
that gets materialized and modern things
in the matrix
does allow us to basically be like yeah
it is
nonsensical psychologically to say oh i
wonder if i'm
awake you know or if i'm really
experiencing this that
that quickly so it's a very
psychologically
or phenomenologically psychologically
compelling uh
experience uh to have that uh
frame so i just wanted to echo that and
emphasize that well that's actually
that's perfect that that fills in a
missing premise in the argument i want
to make
so notice what's happening with with
what grape just said
right the the the we regard it as a
rational conviction but it's not
following from
uh deductive or logical argumentation
it's fall and this is descartes point
it's following from
a direct conformity of the mind with
itself a direct phenomenological
experience
now that is very interesting because now
descartes is actually slipped
something in that is going to be very
problematic because he's given us
two different ways by which we establish
intelligible realness and therefore two
different standards
by which we evaluate if things are real
one is the standard that follows from
logical mathematical argumentation and
therefore says
the mathematical the mathematically
realized properties
are the most real the primary qualities
so the objective mathematical properties
that's what's most real but then he's
given us another argument that goes from
moves from a completely different base
it's not a logical argument
at least initially it's a direct
phenomenological experience which says
no no no
this direct awareness i have of the
realness of my own mind
that's what's most real and everything
else has a derived
reality from that really and now you
have a problem
you what descartes has done in his
argument for dualism
again these very these very convincing
arguments for dualism
and this is an important component of
the mind consciousness problem
is that he has rendered our normative
judgments
about realness perpetually unstable
because we can always set these off
against each other and you can then see
psychology and philosophy in fact i
would argue
the whole intellectual history of the
west since descartes
is constantly vacillating between these
two different normative strategies
and types of claims for what's real you
can either say no no
oh sorry greg you're doing i'm just
gonna really quick so when we start it
off we're going to
we're going to get a much differentiated
picture of mental processes that's part
of where we're headed
so remember phenomenologically this is
mind two
okay and then mind three is getting into
justificatory rationality
right so i just want to highlight that
this
blend actually is going to be
differentiated when we
uh get to the end of our puzzle making
thank you greg thank you for doing that
that's excellent
okay so what what's the vacillation i
was talking about well what we can do is
we can we can go basic
we can uh you know we can be sort of a
realist
of some kind and we can say you know
what's ultimately real and you know
people
hammer on things material things that's
what's real
objective mathematically and everything
else is
so nearly subjective merely an illusion
and then and then other people say what
are you talking about
you know my the my subjective awareness
of my own consciousness
is the most real thing there is to me
everything else
is could just be an illusion or a dream
and then you move towards idealism
and then of course and and like many
other people i don't think
um that kind of idealism is a plausible
alternative
because you get into problems around
solipsism and the
deep history and i think berkeley
basically shows that
that kind of idealism uh requires
something
like a god to explain why things are
persisting outside of our awareness
and then you're in the you're in the
situation of that
your your your model of mind depends on
establish independently establishing the
existence of god
and my response to that is well good
luck with that good luck with that right
and what i will also say in a nod to
your future
is that we're gonna want a system that
shows how these
domains participate in relationship to
each other
in some sort of transactional kind of
pattern
exactly exactly that's that
that's very well said the problem with
both
a kind of uh trenchant materialism
and a trench in subjectivism idealism is
they ultimately don't explain the
problem
that descartes has left us which which
is the deep inter-penetrating
participatory relationship
between in mind and body while they do
our adopt-reductive strategies
of arguing that one of the two poles is
somehow an
illusion which is as greg is nodding is
just to fall prey to the very cartesian
grammar
that needs to be challenged that needs
to be challenged because that grammar if
you're if you
if you follow it consistently is not
going to give you
a stable account of realness and that
and the history that's come out of this
i think is good evidence
for the claim i'm making and i think
greg is not into
and so what that does is i i think it
tells us that
any account of
mind that has the consequence
of rendering our ability to judge
realness
unstable and non-viable is ultimately a
self-defeating
account of mind amen
especially if we can get an inductive to
a best explanation that doesn't do that
doesn't have that problem that would be
perfectly good
okay so i take it that we want to
and so when we talk about this cultural
cognitive grammar
i mean that that that that all of these
disputes
that have keep going back and forth
between our culture
um they all are in dispute with each
other
precisely because they share this common
cultural cognitive grammar
um around mind and body
and realness etc okay so that's the
second argument which means
any attempt to unravel the world not has
to not only
you're now going to see why this is
getting to be a hard problem
it's not only going to deal with well
what do we do how do we
do that while maintaining all of what
we've got from the scientific revolution
because the two
right this model of mind and the
scientific revolution are interwoven
that's hard enough but now we add in the
second thing well you know while you're
at it
in order to address the mind body
problem you need to break out of this
grammar and stabilize what realness is
well that's that's a pretty hard problem
too
that's a pretty hard problem too um okay
so now the third argument from descartes
oh greg do you want to
say anything before i move to the third
argument no is this where we get into
hobbes and uh
yeah exactly that's right perfect yep
nope that's where
i was thinking and then that's going to
bring us into
a more specifically properly
psychological theory i would say a
theory of mind
a theory of cognition that is more
specifically
mathematically experimentally um
open to examination that's what hops
does
so hobbes takes a look at what descartes
has done
and he's deeply like everybody they're
contemporaries
yeah yeah and hobbes even writes to
descartes um
descartes is not very nice to hobbes um
because where you know hobbs
is brilliant but hobbes is not a good
mathematician and descartes knows that
and so he has contempt for hobbes in
that uh in that way
um but descartes is also a bit of a
political
uh courtier the way he responds to
princess elizabeth who
sometimes says some not brilliant things
she sometimes says really good things
too but sometimes she says things but
he's always
oh you're so brilliant and blah blah
blah so they are contemporaries
um but hobbes notices what descartes is
doing
and he says well look well you've been
you've taken away all the
causation all the other jobs that the
mind used to have
and it has one job and one job alone now
it's a purely
epistemic engine and that and it's an
epistemic engine
that operates in a purely mathematical
manner what it does it's a it's an
epistemic engine
a machine for coming up with knowledge
that and that's the all it does it
doesn't do any of that actualizing
any of that embedding any of that
contact with the world it's not doing
any of that
right it's just manipulating
mathematical representations in order to
come up
with the most certain account
of the world and that's all it's doing
and then hobbes looks at that he says
well
the you know the purely mechanical
mathematical
sorry the purely mechanical manipulation
logical manipulation
of uh mathematical propositions well
that's just computation
that's just computation and so he
actually says
uh this is a direct quote by wrathios a
nation which is an old term for
cognition i mean computation he
specifically
advocates the idea that cognition is
computation
people think this is a radical new idea
that came out of you know the computer
revolution
um no it was revised but hobbes
proposes it you see how the
computational model of mind
is actually one of the first children of
the scientific revolution
and so bob's proposes this and then
hobbes does something
really radical with it he says you know
what
we can get rid of all of this cartesian
problem uh you know
because if cognition is computation
well look around because what's
happening they already have they already
have machines
you know very primitive by higher
standards that are capable of doing
addition
right calculation and some of the first
automatons
and they were were being made and they
were right like a mechanical duck
i don't remember where that comes around
but that's a classic
these are the these are the talk of
european civilization
and so hobbs says well can i make uh
something like uh
an automated abacus that can do
a purely mechanical form of computation
and if it's doing computation
then it's cognitive and then i've made a
mind and then i don't have to worry
about all this
immaterial substance and all of that
stuff and what i have is a
a purely computational account of mine
which of course is
a very current proposal strong ai
wrong ai strong ai exactly exactly
now what's descartes argument so
descartes third argument is basically a
series of responses
to hobbs and we have to note this now
it's tempting to think that
is going to do is what sort of going to
invoke you know religious ideas about
the soul and immortality
in order to try and refute hubs but he
doesn't he doesn't do that at all
what he does is he says hobbes you're an
idiot
because your model of mind is not
consistent with the scientific
revolution
eckhart actually within his historical
context
makes scientific arguments against
bob's proposal what are the nature of
those arguments
well he says well and this is this is
brilliant
descartes says well what do we what do
we need to presuppose
is going on in people who are actually
doing science
what do we need to say about their
cognition well their reasoning
okay well what is it to reason well he
says
well reasoning depends on the meanings
of things
and the scientific revolution and with
the destruction
of the aristotelian worldview says there
is no meaning in things
meaning isn't a mathematical extended
material inertial thing meaning is
completely
in the mind it's not a property of
matter
so hobbes how could you possibly
manipulate matter
and get meaning out of it you're not
paying attention to the scientific
revolution matter is inert
it has no tediology to it it has no
internal dynamics
all it does is accidentally hit other
chunks of matter
there is no way you can get meaning
out of matter and then aligned with that
he says
notice when i'm reasoning i'm reasoning
in terms of what's true
but truth is a function of meaning i can
only tell
if something is true if i know what it
means and therefore
truth like meaning is also non-material
so how are you going to give that
capacity
to seek the truth from from a with a
purely material machine and then
look at what we're talking about we're
talking about seeking the truth
that's to act on purpose but you know
what the scientific revolution has shown
us
it's showing us that matter does not act
on purpose
the only thing that's teleological is in
your mind
and then although descartes doesn't make
this third argument as directly we can
make it on his
behalf in terms of implication hobbes
the scientific revolution has
specifically worked by saying
all of the secondary qualities all of
the qualia
are not in the world they're only in the
mind
they're only in the mind therefore
you're not you can't
get them to inhere in a purely
mechanical thing so the scientific
revolution is telling me that mind and
truth
and purpose and qualia are not in matter
and there is no way by manipulating
matter that you will get them to appear
so you're an idiot hawks you're an idiot
now
pops tries to reply by saying well you
know uh
well what's with the meaning what we
could do is we could attach little
pieces of paper
uh to the various beads of the abacus
like cat and matt and da
and is and then we could get it to say
the cat is on the map and then it would
have meaning
and then descartes point and then you
know uh
you know john cerrell just redoes this
with the chinese room argument yes
he just says that manipulation of those
of those physical tokens has no meaning
in and of itself it only has meaning
that you attribute
to it if you put the abacus on the beach
and it moved
the waves moved the abacus so the beads
come to say the cat is on the map
would you think that the the the waves
were communicating meaningfully to you
of course not it right so it's
only when the symbols and we'll come
back to this
it's only when the symbols are used
intentionally in terms of an attributed
meaning
in the pursuit of truth that you
actually get the meaning
that we're talking about when we talk
about
what do we need to presuppose is going
on
in the minds of people who practice
science so describes arguments
all run off the existence of science
they all say given that we're doing
science and we think that science is
getting us
at reality and it's the model of
knowledge notice what that presupposes
and none of those presuppositions line
up with what the scientific
revolution is saying about matter and so
this was a
this is an argument of course that
huglin uh made
uh very famous uh in fact in a book
called
uh artificial intelligence the very idea
because
here's what hughlin is trying to show
that
what greg said earlier strong ayat weak
ai is just let's make machines that do
things that people used to have to do
like in the 1930s computers was the name
of a group of people
that were in your business and you set
anything down that needed to be computed
and now the job that used to be done by
people is now done by a machine or you
used to have to go to a teller
but now that you can go to uh a an
automatic an atm
right and so and that i don't like these
because it sounds pejorative but weak ai
is let's make machines that can do what
people
we used to do and that's a valuable and
important project
absolutely strong ai is this change
is the project of trying to do the
following it's trying to
satisfy and provide evidence and i'll
use greg's term justification
for hobbs claim that cognition
is purely mechanical material
computation so what it's trying to do is
to create an instance of cognition
by creating an instance of commute of
computation
that can reply and give satisfactory
answer
to all of descartes problem strong ai
would be
here is an instance of computation and
it counts as a bona fide
instance of cognition perhaps
consciousness as well
because here's how this model of strong
ai
gives me a plausible response
to the problem of meaning the problem of
purpose
the problem of qualia etc
so notice how the problem of strong ai
is actually bound up with the
world not that greg and i are attempting
to enter
and that's so cool to me i didn't know
about this history
um but as soon as i was hearing about it
oh my god this is the chinese room
problem which
i hope folks who are watching this know
you know this is john searle's
argument against strong ai so so cool
that
descartes and hobbes are stumbling
across this you know
basic uh i would not have guessed that
so
to me that's just really interesting
here's another thing that i'll say
is that um we talked briefly about this
and i think we'll come back
keep coming back this concept of
information
uh like matter and energy this is a very
very
interesting and complicated concept um
and one of the things that we're going
to want to differentiate is information
theoretic models
which actually connect deeply to
mathematics somebody
claude shannon sort of the newton of
information is concerned with
information and the really the reduction
of uncertainty connects into
thermodynamics et cetera okay um and
and then there's the information
semantic
that's right element okay so i am
hearing one way to potentially hear this
narrative
uh through this particular lens is
saying hobbs is basically hey can we
just do this by via information
theoretic
you know computation right and and the
car's like no
because you have semantic meaning making
you know that
that makes us as embodied entities that
are actually deciphering
truth and meaning and reality etc well
said
very well said greg and so yeah that
technical sense of meaning and that
semantic sense
sorry that technical sense of
information and that
semantic meaning oriented sense of
information
um uh trying to bridge between them
theoretically
is a difficult task and i think i
mentioned
i might have mentioned the last time you
know there's work by uh people very
recent we're trying
to wrestle with that and the thing we
have to avoid and this is what i think
greg is pointing to
and this is why the problem formulation
again is so central if you don't
keep these clearly distinct you will
equivocate between them
and you will say well what's the problem
you know there's information
in the technical sense in my nervous
system and that's just becomes
information in my mind
and why is their mind body problem
that's because you've equivocated
between these two totally different
senses of information
and therefore you haven't solved the
problem you've just fudged over it
and so this is another version of this
problem
and it's one of the central problems in
strong ai and and
cyril uh uh point points us to it
but as greg said i think cyril's
argument is just a modern one of cyril's
argument
this is a modern version of what was
going on between descartes and hops
is that you know the the within
a strong ai we see a version of the mind
body problem as the technical
information
semantic information problem how do we
bridge between them
in a completely non-equivocal
and consistent manner how do we
scientifically you know integrate them
or unify them and that is actually a
very hard problem
and we're gonna we're gonna see that the
proposals that uh try to bridge that
are going to invoke notions of agency um
autonomy self-organization
uh things like that amen so what they're
going to do is
actually sneak aristotle back in in
order to try and deal with the problem
that has been given to us uh by decode
yes
so uh let's recap what we've got
uh we've got three arguments uh we've
got
the argument we've just done which is um
the argument that
uh cognition can't be mechanical
material computation
uh because the scientific revolution has
removed all the properties
central to scientific reasoning from
matter right and then you would just be
in a huge performative contradiction
according to descartes
if you try to uh derive scientific
reasoning from matter
we just did earlier the comparative
realness argument
the consequence we uh the the the mind
is comparatively
more real to us but what descartes does
is slip in a new way
of determining what's real uh that's in
contrast to the
mathematical logical way of determining
what's real
he now puts in this direct
phenomenological experiential
participatory sense of realness and then
those two senses of realness are now
gonna because he just gives us both
and then they're gonna smash into each
other for centuries
uh and then we're back and then the
original argument was
uh different kinds of properties
different kinds of stuff and we saw that
that
uh also saddles us with the mind-body
problem so there's
where we're at so far in formulating the
problem how's that
i think that's a i think that's a really
nice summary
of what is emerging right here in in
terms of the modernist
western modernist uh sense-making system
uh that's coming off of you know that
has its history very strongly of course
in the catholic
you know christian ideology and now is
making these transitions
and this is then okay you have this
thing
mind that is representing the world out
here
you know and there's a primary world and
then you have a secondary mapping of
that
and it is your position in relationship
to that uh that allows you to determine
what is true
um and then we hand it that m and then
of course then that's
mind body problem is actually we'll wait
a minute we're basically there's a dual
world
ontology here that's very very that
difficult to
recognize so so let's let's so when we
greg and i will say mind body and mind
brain problem but let's remember
that it's actually always a mind brain
problem or a mind body problem
a mind mind problem because remember i
can't pick up on greg's mind
and it's also a mind world problem right
if the only thing my mind actually
directly knows
is itself then shouldn't
i be completely skeptical of any
knowledge
about the world out there called
mathematical world that's right
i generally refer to it when i'm
sparking specifically off the tree of
knowledge
i talk about the mind matter problem is
usually because then i'm going to come
back and bring the concept of matter
in relationship to mind and add life and
culture
and show a nested hierarchy and then
that will change but so
but yes it's that's another is it mind
brain is it mind body is it mind matter
is it mind world is it mine
these are all just good examples of wow
this the complexity of this grammar
dynamic is really profound
yeah that was very well said great so i
want to now talk
about um a little bit more of because we
have some time and then i want to
that way i can give sort of maximal
opportunity for greg next time
uh to take the lead uh because some of
you are probably tired of
me talking so much and i want to hear
what greg has to say
and he i and he has expertise on in
areas i do not
um so i want to talk a little bit about
uh uh going back again to descartes
and getting clear about a couple other
parts of the problem formulation
that we need to uh clarify we i believe
we mentioned these earlier at the
beginning
sort of the nature problem and the
generation or function problem
uh so first of all we can now clarify
what the nature or the generation
problem is
the nature of the generation problem is
basically the problem of
solving these problems that descartes
has given us it's the problem of
how do we get back together uh mind and
matter i'll use greg's terms right now
uh now because
most people because they regard um
the dualism as implausible because of
all of these problems we're opening up
around it
they would they want to account for how
does
mind emerge out of matter um
so we could get into a long attempt to
defend that against
idealisms and other things but since
this is what the
the most people are doing that's how i'm
going to pose the problem
but if you want to you can always think
about it is how do i come up with a
world view
that reconciles the inter penetration
and the inter-participation of mind and
body
so how is it that we have something like
consciousness
in a physical body that's the nature
problem that's the generation problem
explaining to me the nature of
consciousness that
gives a way of answering of all these
problems that descartes has given us
resolving them so that there's it's no
longer problematic to say
that i have consciousness and a body and
that they are intimately
interpenetrating and causally connected
in some fashion right that's that's the
nature problem
yep what's the function problem well the
function problem is also
uh coming out of this uh if you it's
like
what's consciousness for because i'm
going to
remember we talked about how descartes
didn't know all the important properties
of mind
so one of them has been post-freud the
discovery of the unconscious and then
chomsky
adds a tremendous amount to that and
here's the idea
a lot of that computation
that descartes says is what mind is
is running unconsciously
i'm forming you know my visual system is
forming right it's doing some kind of
computation so i'm forming
a perception of greg right now and
something in my hearing is parsing the
noises that come out of his mouth
and and somehow that's making i not i
don't know
how any i'm not aware of how any of
that's happening the only place where
awareness is
is that the end result yeah it's at the
end
so if all of the heavy lifting and all
of the computational work
i'm using descartes language here in
hobbs language here is going on
unconsciously what's consciousness more
what's consciousness and why and and and
is it's sense that it's somehow
central or important to your agency is
that just an illusion
is that just an illusion that's the
function problem what does consciousness
do and you know how you know how to do
a lot of [ __ ] that you don't know how to
do i'm
equivocating on the word no here of
course yeah no procedurally
and no existence wise but not know
analytically or explicitly
right ride a bike right i mean it's
amazing how much
um and and yet we're just aware of what
we're aware of in a particular way so
this all there's an enormous amount of
embodied knowing
that takes place without consciousness
so why do we have it
so that's the function problem now what
i want to briefly talk about is i want
to talk about how
um uh how descartes
actually wrestles with these problems i
don't think he resolves them but
his wrestling is instructive because
i take descartes to have the this
insight that these two problems need to
be solved
uh in an interconnected manner that if
you try and
solve the nature problem without solving
the function problem you're ultimately
going to have
an unsatisfactory account because what
would it be to say
how something exists without saying
explaining how it functions how
it causally interacts with the world and
the reverse is the case
how could i possibly explain how
something spunk how something functions
if i didn't have some sense of what it
what its ontological nature
was what what its nature is uh and so
i think we should follow descartes
in trying to uh answer these two
problems
in an integrated fashion now that is not
typically what's done
there's been a there's been a couple of
recent papers that are trying to do this
but typically
some of the biggest theories global
workspace theory is largely a theory
of the function of consciousness the
integrated information theory of tononi
is largely a theory of the nature
of consciousness and there's been a
recent paper that's tried to put the two
together because people are realizing
hey we really should be answering these
two problems
in an integrated fashion so we've have
along and this is where
greg could perhaps speak more to it than
i could we have a long history within
science and neuroscience
of not tackling until very recently
not tackling these two problems in an
integrated fashion
together and that has i think further
and sorry i keep saying this that has
made this problem even more difficult
and it's kind of uh a deceptive kind of
difficulty
because it looks like we're attempting
to solve
untangle the world not but the degree to
which we're pursuing a functional theory
or a nature theory independent of the
other i think this is really to which
we're actually
um still making the whole thing
more deeply problematic more deeply
problematic
now what's interesting about descartes
is
he has a sense of where they come
together
and this is a little bit tricky because
it requires me
going back to the example of the dog
remember we talked about how descartes
was
willing to sort of uh you know maybe
this is apocryphal maybe not
uh you know do a live dissection of a
dog because dogs have no
consciousness so therefore they're not
feeling any pain
etc which i find just a massively
improbable
uh claim right and morally
well orally um
so but
what many people don't realize and
here's where i'm very dependent on the
excellent work done by
uh bill seeger on this is that descartes
didn't think
that animals were not were not
intelligent
right and this is one of and this is
another thing that i'm going to want to
challenge which is this dichotomy
between intelligence and consciousness
and notice how much the function
question
can lead you to well i can most of my
intelligence is happening unconsciously
so therefore there's no deep connection
between consciousness intelligence
but that actually flouts against the way
we
practice the way we practice is we
generally attribute consciousness where
we find clear behavioral evidence for
intelligence
so now what was going on in descartes
let's go back
describe said well he realized there was
a problem
it seemed like animals learn and it
seems like animals solve
problems he could see dogs doing this
you could teach a dog something
i mean human beings have been teaching
dogs for a long time and dogs can
you know a dog can come up you can even
see a dog doing you know when the dogs
do this with their head
and their and then they seem to they
they solve a problem
and it's like so there's intelligence
there so
they don't have they don't have minds or
what descartes would call soul
so what's going on well descartes had
the idea
that the the brain had states
there are brain states that reliably
co-vary
with the world so what do i mean by
reliable covariance think of the way
your thermostat reliably co-varies with
the temperature in your room
so in that sense and we're going to come
this is going to be contentious
but in that sense the thermostat
represents
the temperature in the room because it
reliably co-varies with it
it allows the thermostat to reliably
discriminate
between different states in the world
and then act accordingly
it will turn your furnace on or off
so in a more complicated and
sophisticated fashion descartes
understands this
the dog has brain states that co-vary
with the world
that allow it to reliably discriminate
between different states affairs in the
world
so that it can do it can reliably
differentiate its behavior
so that it can achieve its goals we'll
we'll we'll sort of not pay too much
attention to that
right now because that sounds like
teleology and uh they curl but
the idea is that you have something like
um brain states sorry we have brain
states that are something like
representations and here's where
astute people and that are watching us
might say ah but isn't he giving in
isn't he giving in to hobbes here
because isn't that what hobbes said
right and then here's where descartes
makes the difference
descartes said ah but those aren't
actually representations
and descripts actually borne out by sort
of current philosophy of mind because
current philosophy of mind
there's a one of the most central
accounts of mental representation
is the idea that representations are
things in the head
the brain whatever that reliably covari
with the world
but most people say that's an inadequate
account
of representation because co-variation
does not pick up
the specificity that representation does
so here's this
so there's something in my head that's
reliably co-varying with it
is it covariating with phone
material object gift given to john
thing i bought in 2016. those are
all different representations and this
is important what i'm now going to say
of different aspects of the same
thing the covariation is co-varying with
all of them
but my representation
a particular aspect of it
exactly turn it around
every representation is inherently
aspectual i'll make this argument in
more detail later
and and people can see more
comprehensive arguments about this
but the number of properties
that are causally available and this is
technical information to me
all of the properties that are actually
instantiated in this
it's combinatorially explosive it's vast
right
so any way in which i represent it
as a phone or as a potential weapon i'm
selecting out of all of that information
a subset that i find relevant
and it's not just sort of
higgledy-piggledy like when i think of
this as a phone
it it forms an integrated hole so how
out of all that subset
sort of out of all that information the
subset of information in the technical
sense
that is relevant to me that
that and and the the piece of
information are relevant to each other
and they are relevant to the actions i'm
going to direct
at the object so i'm doing all this
relevance realization
every representation is inherently
aspectual
and for descartes
what he sees happening is that what
consciousness does is it aspectualizes
the co-variation so that it becomes a
particular specific representation
and john cerl makes a remarkably similar
argument
in the rediscovery of the mind in the
90s again i don't think that's a
coincidence
because of how cartesian his view uh
really is so
here's here's the idea i got this
co-variation
and it may allow intelligent behavior
but it's not representation it doesn't
have meaning
it can't be evaluated for truth because
it needs to be
aspectualized first and all
representations
are aspectual and that's what
consciousness does
consciousness is a process of
aspectualization
this is why for descartes you had to
always be able to
when you were doing an argument you
could you had to be able to at some you
had to be able to get the whole argument
in mind at one time you had to have like
a flash of insight
it had to go through an aspect shift
because only then
where you was is it was it's something
that you could reason on
only then were you capable of
determining meaning and therefore truth
so
notice what descartes is doing here it's
really interesting
i'm not claiming and i know greg is not
claiming this is not
any kind of solution this is not an
untangling but notice what he's doing
he's talking about a process that is
central
to the epistemic function of the mind
that and what this what this does is it
gives it gives a function to
consciousness
consciousness basically aspectualizes
covariation into representations
and readies that information for reason
which is very much like in many ways the
global workspace
and other models about access
consciousness as
poising information for you for
reasoning so descartes got that there
but it's also looks like he's giving an
account
and i don't know how much he was quite
explicitly aware of this
of how mind emerges
from matter if we could figure out how
we do
a spectralization in
within a physical process
then we could also perhaps explain
the emergence of consciousness via that
spectralization
i don't think this is complete i don't
think it's adequate i'm not saying that
but what i'm saying is
notice how brilliant this is because
he's operating
he's offering an integrated response to
both the function problem
right and the nature problem here's one
of the things i do want to argue
i do think that we can give and greg and
i are going to argue about physicalism
and i know that
and it's basically and it's but i do
think we can give because that's what i
attempt to do
i think we can give a scientific account
of aspectualization in terms of a
process called relevance realization
and i've already invoked it here but if
we could explain it
um ultimately in terms of brain well
embodied brain coupling to the world
functionality
then we would have an account of how a
spectralization at least
emerges within an otherwise scientific
world view and then that would also link
directly to the functionality
of consciousness now there's a lot more
like look at my hands
there's a lot more that has to be done
but what i'm trying to do is show you
the promise
of zeroing in on a
point where the nature problem and the
function problem seems to continue to
come together
which is in the process of aspect
realization and i think that's an
important lesson
to take forward from descartes and we're
going to see again this
these connections between consciousness
and aspect realization
uh representation and relevance
realization
ramifying through a lot of the accounts
of consciousness
that we're going to take a look at
brilliant brilliant
so let me summarize some of this in
terms of
uh so where what i'm hearing so this
aspect realization
uh is then harmonizing at you know
aspects of this co-variation somehow
right and then we talk about the
function like global neuronal workspace
we're gonna
globally make available okay some sort
of harmonizing a whole brain way to get
the
system on the same frequency yes
okay and that's and so and let's also
make a distinction here between
sort of the ontogenetic and proximal
definition of functional like
okay how do we manage this conversation
and what is my consciousness doing
um versus we haven't talked about darwin
but of course when we talk about
darwin coming on the scene right yeah we
talk about the phylogenetic
functionality
yeah right and then nature built this in
phylogenetically for certain kinds of
purposes
okay and i'll just put a little plug
here for behavioral investment
theory framework for understanding what
the nervous system is trying to do it's
very consistent with
carl tristan's work and others okay
basically the nervous system is trying
to direct your energy
work effort all right toward
the good and the bad you know whatever
is correlated with uh
survival and reproductive success okay
and what it says is it sort of downloads
a model of that work investment you got
a model of
the animal in relationship to the
environment paths of different kinds of
work effort
okay and what so what the what you're
trying to do then is create
a model that allows you to make
predictions
so that your investments pay off all
right
when that's going fine great when not
the system needs to reboot and check
okay when it gets surprised in a
particular type of way
all right so one of the things then that
we may start to do phylogenetically is
maybe some of this aspectualization
pertains to predictability expectation
yeah okay yeah and then when things are
not expected then the things light up in
a particular way
to try to get them to model uh into a
more expected route
and if that's the case then this aspect
realization tying into prediction
tying into work investment of this
phenomenology
really starts to have a phylogenetic and
an ontogenetic functionality
um in a way that you know starts to tie
stuff together
excellent well said um so let's
there are probably deep connections
between the capacity for
aspectualization and model formation i
think
and there's deep connections between
aspectualization and relevance
realization
and i think there's deep connections
between predictive modeling
relevance realization and intelligence
and therefore though we will turn out
though i will argue and i think greg
agrees with me and this is
part of i think some of my work uh plugs
into
the history of knowledge continuum is
that um there is a
a deep connection even continuity
uh between the processes that make you
intelligent
and the processes that make you
conscious um
which has really strong implications
for strong ai uh actually
um so that's where we're heading that's
where we're heading
um and so next time uh greg's gonna
take us through how this very complex
and tortured grammar
uh ramifies through the history of
psychology right the field then tries to
say okay we'll scientize this thing
right and then ultimately what happens
is you get a
multi pre a multi-pre paradigmatic
emergence multi meaning many
pre meaning that they're unable to
develop a fully functioning paradigm
okay so newton paradigmatically
organizes classical mechanics for 200
years and really remains as a classical
mechanic
paradigm okay so we're going to try the
system is going to try to wake up and
say hey should we
can we scientifically paradigmatically
organize the mind
from this logic and then what we'll see
is the answer is actually no
that's the short answer it's no it isn't
that interesting
no you're not able to do it i look
forward to this this is going to be very
very exciting very interesting so uh
thank you my good friend
uh this was thank you that was a great
uh articulation you know it really
really nailed some really central points
i enjoyed it thank you very much
and thank you for all all of you who
have given us your time and attention
and look forward to seeing you next time
when we continue
uh to try as best we can at least to
some degree
on tangling the world not